Partho Biswas

Software Engineer - iOS

7+ years of professional experience in iOS platform, well-versed in Clean-Modular architecture, UI/UX, algorithm and data-structure. I built high performant apps, used by millions, and codebase that scales to large team of engineers, drove the product vision for my company.

Dhaka, Bangladesh +8801722455000 partho.maple@gmail.com github.com/partho-maple linkedin.com/in/partho-biswas

WORK EXPERIENCE

iOS Software Architect/Consultant

Self-employed / Freelance

March, 2020 - Current

Remote

- Helped implementing complex features and architectural issues for different startups to achieve their product goals
- Contributed to open source projects like WooCommerce iOS app and created few open source projects that gained 600+ stars
- Solved 700+ algorithmic problems on different platforms (Leetcode & AlgoExpert) and read 10+ iOS books

iOS Software Architect

Aurea Software

June, 2017 - February, 2020

Remote, through Crossover.com

- Increased the revenue by 5% for the company by delivering the Jive Daily app, leading a team of 4 developers
- Rearchitectured and developed Aurea-CRM app from Objective-C to Swift that scales to 12+ concurrent engineers with 90% Unit Testability
- Rearchitectured monolithic codebase to Clean-Modular architecture that improved startup time by 50% and build time by 70%
- Designed & developed the APIs and network layer collaborating with cross-functional teams, improving network data consumption by 20%

Senior Software Engineer (iOS)

IPVision Canada Inc.

September, 2014 - September, 2017

- Dhaka, Bangladesh
- Achieved \sim 5 million users, on ringID app, developed from scratch with a team of 6 engineers
- Implemented VoIP, Streaming and Store module/SDK for iOS with 95% Unit Test Coverage
- Developed custom image library that Improved image rendering quality and speed by 40% leading a team of 2 engineers
- Developed custom UI/UX components in Swift, used in multiple inhouse apps
- Improved app stability by 70% by developing custom debugging tool to troubleshoot on cross language project

Software Engineer (iOS)

Code Knight Solutions/ X-10 Technology.

September, 2013 - August, 2014

Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Developed flagship VoIP dialer app for iOS and iPad that generated \$125K revenue in it's first year
- Codeveloped inhouse VoIP SDK for SIP/SDP, audio and video codecs.
- Improved G729 codec performance by replacing arithmetic operations with bitwise operations that reduced audio latency by 20%

SKILLS

- iOS, Swift, Objective-C
- MVP, MVVM, MVVM-C, VIPER, VIP
- Unit/UI Testing (TDD, BDD)
- iOS performance tuning, App profiling
- RESTful, JSON, Websocket

- Design Patterns, SOLID, Jira, Git, Agile
- Reactive programming (RxSwift)
- Continuous Integration & Delivery
- Algorithms & Problem Solving
- UIKit, CoreData, Alamofire, AutoLayout
- C++, Python
- Audio Video streaming technologies
- WebRTC, SIP, SDP, RTP, H.264
- VOIP, Media & Network programming

NOTEWORTHY

- Ranking #1 Swift GitHub developer and #2 Objective-C GitHub developer in Bangladesh on GitHub-awards
- Solved 700+ algorithmic problems on different platforms (Leetcode.com & AlgoExpert.io). Enthusiastic competitive programmer
- Currently have 2K+ reputation and among Top 10% iOS, 20% Objective-C and 30% Swift Contributor on StackOverflow.com

EDUCATION

Shahjalal University of Science and Technology

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science and Engineering

Sylhet, Bangladesh February, 2009 - May, 2013

PROJECTS

ringID

Proprietor: Ring Inc, concern of IPVision Canada Inc.

- Architectured and developed audio and video calling SDK, image SDK and module from planning to production.
- Optimized the audio and video codecs to work on low latency and internet speed

ringID Messenger

Proprietor: Ring Inc, concern of IPVision Canada Inc.

- Implemented custom video filtering and live image rendering algorithm reducing GPU throughput by 20%
- Architectured and developed audio/video calling SDK solely. Led a team of 2 developers

Jive Daily (Product Line)

Proprietor: Jive Software, concern of Aurea Software

- Developed messaging system, facebook like newsfeed solely. Codeveloped networking, database. Contributed on almost whole app.
- Achieved 90% unit test coverage while using customized MVVM and service oriented architecture
- Managed MDM servers and configurations for MobileIron, AirWatch

Aurea CRM.pad

Proprietor: Aurea Software

- Led the development of Aurea-CRM app from legacy MVC, Objective-C/C++ codebase to latest Swift
- Improved performance and memory usage by 30%, achieved 95% unit test coverage while using VIPER and TDD
- Developed complete Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery pipeline.

Gold Dialer

Proprietor: Code Knight Solutions Inc.

Wrote the app solely from planning to production including VoIP SDK